<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
<properties>
	<title>Castle Contrib</title>
</properties>

<body>

<intro>
<p>
After interesting and valuable contributions to Castle Project have circulated on the internet we decided to offer a separated repository so author can contribute their projects and have it released together with the main releases.
</p>
</intro>

<section id="whatisit">
<title>What is it?</title>
<p>
The contrib is a separated project with low entry barrier. It's <strong>not officialy supported and/or maintained by the Castle team</strong>. The following rules apply:
<ul>
<li>Contribution is a volunteer work</li>
<li>he author donates his/her work and releases it under a license compatible with the Apache Software License (in other words, no GPL or LGPL license, please)</li>
<li>The very minimum of documentation must be supplied on the contrib area of this very wiki</li>
<li>The author promises to make an additional effort to keep his/her contribution in sync with the rest of the trunk, otherwise the Castle team can decide unilaterally to not include the contribution in future releases</li>
<li>If the contribution was created/implemented during work hours, it's assumed that the company the author works for is aware and has agreed to release the contribution freely, through an open source license</li>
</ul>
</p>

<section>
<title>Example of contributions for the Contrib area</title>
<p>
    *  Any tool that makes life of Castle developers and users simpler
    * Any extension/derivative work based on the Castle code 
</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>What does not fit as contribution for the Contrib area</title>
<p>
    *  Patches and/or bug fixes: these can be sent directly to the castle-devel list or through our issue tracker
    * Documentation: these can be done in place 
</p>
</section>

</section>

<section>
<title>Contribution's future</title>
<p>
If the contribution proves that it's valuable for our users, it might graduate and go to the main source trunk. The decision is made by the Castle PMC and under consent of the contribution author. It's likely that in these cases the author be elected as a committer.
</p>
<p>
For these situations, the code needs to be re-licensed to 'Apache Software License' and adhere to Castle code standards 
</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>The Contrib repository</title>
<p>
All committers have access to the contrib repository and are free to make any required modification.
</p>

<p>
http://svn.castleproject.org/svn/castlecontrib/
</p>

<p>
If you have gained access to the contrib repository (someone has generated a login and password for you) then please use the SSL version:
</p>

<p>
https://svn.castleproject.org/svn/castlecontrib/ 
</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Site map for the Contrib area</title>

<sitemap select="castle/others/contrib"/>

</section>

</body>
</document>
